<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Scharmorton model for FlightGear  
  Copyright (C) Herbert Wagner 2016
  This file is licensed under the GPL license
-->
<PropertyList>

 <!-- Specific keys -->
 <title>Scharmorton Roziere Ballon by HerbyW 2016 Version 3.1</title>
 <key>
  <name>q</name>
  <desc>Step 1: Initialize everything, wait till all ballonets have the same value</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>W</name>
  <desc>Step 4: Filling Helium to -3% for take off</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>D</name>
  <desc>Blower On, use after declining to fill in the air-cell to maximal value</desc>
 </key> 
 <key>
  <name>d</name>
  <desc>Blower Out</desc>
 </key> 
 <key>
  <name>G</name>
  <desc>Helium out</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>g</name>
  <desc>Helium in</desc>
 </key> 
 <key>
  <name>w</name>
  <desc>Show current on-ground weight.</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>F</name>
  <desc>Open Parachute valve.</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>f</name>
  <desc>Close Parachute valve.</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>R</name>
  <desc>Rip envelope.</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>E</name>
  <desc>Anchor</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>e</name>
  <desc>Turn Valve left</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>r</name>
  <desc>Turn Valve right</desc>
 </key>
 <key>
  <name>y</name>
  <desc>Change Model View and Panel View</desc>
 </key>
 <!-- Handling instructions. -->
 <text>
Panel Manual Scharmorton by HerbyW
 
Preparing for Take-off
 
Open HUD "h", you see a lot of values.
Make the wind settings or metar data activ (see details below).
Press 1. Temp or "q": we get now all temperatures to the outside temperatur and get the ballon fixed on ground.
Now press 2. HotAir, blows the air-cell with hot air to some level. Wait!
This is a hot-fill and the cell temerature will go to 60-65 deg.
Now press 3. Heli, fills the helium ballonets to some level. Wait!
(The HUD shows you the filling values, also the 3 volume-meters)
Wait for both ballonets to get filled, if you mess it up you will get strange weight issues. 
Wait till the ballon is filled and in a standing position!
Press 4.TakeOff or "W" to set the helium cells to start conditions.

Take off

Start the burner with the switches on the panel, be aware that the burner-system has 4500 horse powers!
After a few seconds the ballon will start to lift 2-5 m, the fixed holding lines will be still activ.
Shut down the burner if the ballon starts to rise up!

No ballast dropping! It is the fuel for your burner :)
No need for the payload menue! All values are calculated now.
Now you may loose the fixed lines and start your flight. (Pressing "E").

In flight

Helium buoyancy mass ("g" more Helium in, "G" Helium out) OR fire on or out will get you to the desired height.
Descending: Helium in little steps out "G", maybe use Parachute-valve ("F" on "f" out), watch Volume-Meters!
Use the blower "D" on, "d" out, to fill the air-cell after descending, and make the burner more effectiv.
Your flight direction is the white arrow in the compass,
adjust the airplane symbol by using the turn-valves "e" left, "r" right
or the Autopilot switch on the right bottom "Orientation Drift Controller".
Parachute Controller and Descending Controller you may set activ to controll
the maximum vertical speed of 3 m/s (more will get you into unstable flight).
 
Befor Landing
Try to get a declinging rate of not more than -0.3 m/s.
Set anchor "E", it will get you down if in contact with the ground and hold you at your landing position.

Ater touch down

Open the Rip-valve "R", watch animation. You flight is finished now. You may make a new flight, just start from the top again.

Or you take off again without opening the rip-valve. Air and Helium and Temeratur is key for getting up again.
 
Maximal altitude 12200 m (ca 40000 ft)
Maximal speed with jet-streams: +300 km/h
 
Tip's and tricks
Sometimes the ballon start with a vertical speed of 30 m/s, if it happens just wait till it comes down
and start normal, or use a different starting position.

Change windspeed to change speed of the balloon:

Weather Conditions: Fair weather -- detailed weather -- advanced settings
Advanced weather Configuration: realistic weather, no terrain presampling!, Wind settings - Wind model: aloft interpol -- Wind Configuration

300/3  20/45  90/80  150/115  210/150  270/175  290/250  270/250 260/250

This setting illuminates a heavy jetsream to the east, so that everyone can make the same flight conditions
and a lot of differnt tasks may be done! FL00 is sea-level! Have fun! 

Most information is from Cameron Ballons (UK), for more vist the webpage and get the manual for Hot-Air-Balloning!
This version for Flightgear is handling most of it to get you the most realistic fun out of it.
Copyright by Herbert Wagner 09-2016.

EXTRA FEATURE
without helium you may use it as normal hot air ballon! (Do not use then any helium depending actions like altitude controller)
</text>
</PropertyList>